yeah I'm just going to repeat that
sentence okay good Rebecca
[Music]
basically he says uh the skill
of turning a problem into what
wow success yeah I hate this word
opportunities so don't
uh turn it into something really cool
all right uh means
things that are blocking you turn out to
be things that supercharge you okay
if you can't turn
problems into successes
then uh there's a danger you will give
up your practice completely okay so it's
not just that you need this skill
to turn a problem into a opportunity or
success you if you don't develop that
skill there's a chance you will give up
okay that problems will overwhelm you
and you'll you'll say this is too much
diamond mountain had huge problems we
every every year here for 20 years we
had huge challenges
and we just busted through you know and
now it's it is the largest I think
Retreat Center in the in the Western
Hemisphere maybe in the world
and uh it's cool and you just have to
keep going and you have to be stubborn
Dharma stubborn
okay
my wife has a stubborn husband uh
all right uh next picture who's on that
it's a businesswoman yeah uh
so keep that well let's keep that image
in mind okay she's a successful young
lady all right
then he starts the listing a special
disaster
for a Dharma person and he says Cosa
means
[Music]
you get a good position
you get a promotion at work you know and
and you become like a vice president or
something all right and he says disaster
the position is a disaster okay
Dharma people get a position then check
Jack means they start to get uh proud of
their position oh now I'm the assistant
assistant director of ACI you know and
then the success becomes an obstacle so
turn the obstacles into success
but be careful that your successes don't
become obstacles it's an interesting
twist you know he says he says
here the third fourth word
Chapa means uh Dharma practitioner means
Dharma
Champa means a Dharma ER
okay a Dharma is
okay and he says he says many a Dharma
is has been ruined by success
or means they lost their practice they
got all wrapped up in their position and
they lost their practice so
uh
problems is a is a danger if you don't
know how to turn them into opportunities
and then opportunities are endangering
after you get after you turn the problem
into an opportunity the opportunity
becomes a danger so he says keep a
middle way keep a middle way okay
it doesn't mean by the way that you
shouldn't be a director or an assistant
director you just can't have Jake Jake
means uh
Pride or something in Yiddish Jack means
something else
uh so I was in the diamond business we
all speak Yiddish you know
[Music]
some people get some money at their job
means what
sure means their Dharma falls down
slips on the ice right in the Sochi
means uh they get all wrapped up in the
things they can buy with the money that
they got and you could say Tesla disease
okay and it gets worse you get a small
Tesla
and then you're like then Elon Musk
makes Tesla zz3 and now all your friends
say you don't have a zz3 yet you know
what's wrong with you and you're like oh
God now I gotta upgrade my Tesla
and then he keeps coming out with new
ones just for those people
so uh learn to
he says means
once you get some money
you get uh tempted to keep buying better
and better things which is why you're so
lucky to have fundraising from from ACI
and
and diamond mountain can relieve you of
this problem
uh I'm just kidding all right and by the
way we're not making money and we're all
Rob my account went under zero last week
Jiggy it was exciting
for all my creditors uh gosh
some people get discouraged when things
mess up okay
so he says you have to keep a
middleweight should
if you can't learn to
thread a middle way between success and
problems you'll never be a good Dharma
practitioner okay you gotta keep your
head
things are going bad keep your head but
also
if things aren't going well keep your
head all right because all the money is
gonna go away in one day all right
you're gonna lose it all in one day the
more you get it everybody loses all
their money everybody so you got to get
mentally ready for it and then you don't
freak out when the day comes okay
he says uh
it's almost better that you never heard
the Dharma
then if you heard the Dharma and you
blew it
so you've been cursed at Diamond
Mountain
uh you heard the Dharma
so it's almost worse it's almost better
if you've never heard it if you just
passed by on Highway 10 and went to the
Indian restaurant and then kept going to
New Mexico and you never stopped here uh
it's less Bad Karma than trying to do
Dharma and then giving it up
by the way for in tibetan for sugang
okay cool means uh
it doesn't mean cool it means cool cool
means uh
you you try you know cocheppa means you
pretend
to to do some Dharma and then you blow
it
so cool is a kind of a very
messing work all right
so here it means
you try to do a bit of Dharma and then
you mess up
that's really lousy my teacher can
reputation some of you know knew him
he I don't know he specialized in these
English words like that's lousy you know
what I mean that's really loud he was on
a kick for a while how many probably
remembers
he watched baseball for a while then all
his English was baseball you know we're
gonna do a double header today
[Music]
so therefore it's very important to
learn
uh to make sure that when problems come
up
you don't let them hurt your practice
and you turn them into some kind of
opportunities to to make to be
successful
Danny uh outline some different ways to
turn problems into opportunities for
wild success and he says there's two
ways uh day law
a you had I'll give fifty dollars
oh yeah
huh
yeah who who said yeah transforming 50
bucks collect from Gigi Tim you don't
get to bet ah yeah girl means
transformation that's what you did
during your two-day Retreat right
here it says you can transform problems
with Samba or with jorwa
okay sampa means with your intentions
means with your actual actions so sampa
comes before Joy one okay so he says
look you can
you can transform problems
with your intention mentally or with
your actions okay and it probably you
should do both okay
uh then he says the first one has two
subcategories which is very
by the way he was a he was a low-level
geshe from Geron house
get on College one of the 12 colleges of
ceramic pobankarimpache the greatest
teacher of of the 20th century
uh was a was the lowest level of the
geshes
and so am I so we're like
okay uh
all right I just got into the game okay
anyway
uh
the high level guess she takes an extra
12 years and I wasn't ready to do that
because I had other stuff to do but
okay
low level means 20 years
higher level means 30 years and I'm like
I started 15 years late so I'm I'm gonna
have all my hair gone be that time I
okay
Denny says a weird thing you can
transform with your intentions in two
different ways the first one is with
actions so it gets a little confusing
and the second one is with your
Viewpoint okay and what's that mean
we're going to talk about don't worry
about it
tombony here's the first one
llama chepa
quotes the offering to llamas okay
okay which he's been on a llama chip a
role here right
he's been quoting La machupa a lot and
he's been quoting the
seven
Point Mojo yeah he's been working on
those two texts basically
and he says
means the outside world in independent
means the pot
that holds all the people it's the
outside physical world and then Jim
means the stuff in the pot which means
all the people and all the animals in
the world so he says you got the outside
world which is the pot that holds
everything
and then you've got all the people and
animals that are in the pond and he says
pop and
people
including animals because in tibetan and
Sanskrit
animals are called people
Kong Sak or purusha
uh when we say people in Tibetan or
Sanskrit it refers to all living things
automatically it's very cool we don't
distinguish between
human people and animal people okay
okay so he says Dickman
uh that that
they're offering to llamas
the verse starts with uh the world and
the contents of the world
are filled with bad Deeds okay the world
the pop and the contents in the pot are
full of Bad Karma okay and where does he
go with that
I'm going to read you the I think I put
the English there Rebecca
yeah there's the English you can kind of
scroll down slow
uh the world and every being who lives
upon this world
are filled with the results of every
wrong ever done
let a shower of suffering fall of things
I never wanted fall on who
I'm me okay and here's the beginning of
the transformation
okay here's the beginning of the
transformation process I pray
that all the bad karma in the world
should be dumped on me
okay that's My Prayer by the way be
careful what you pray for okay like you
got to be mentally ready before you do
this practice okay so don't be
if you ask for it make sure you you're
ready because it that's that stuff will
come all right uh let all the bad karma
come down on me bless me to see it all
as a way that all the fruits of my own
bad Deeds are finally exhausted so if I
agree
to take on the problems of all people
it will kill my bad days
okay agreeing to take on all Bad Karma
cancels your Bad Karma got it
kind of interesting it's a it's I don't
know if it's a good deal
take on 8 billion people's Bad Karma in
one of the eight billion is cleaned out
okay
I'm not sure it sounds like a
ACI fundraising deal or something okay
uh here we go bless me to learn to turn
every problem that ever comes to me into
a path that
takes me further okay wild success all
right so bless me to do that
and by the way he keeps the lamrim
teaching Style
is to quote a book that the students are
supposed to know
but we're kind of
advanced
people
who spend our day in the cell phone and
we can't memorize two lines of scripture
because we don't have time because of
our time saving device
bonus
time saving devices taking all your time
all right Lo Jones
let's go to the lojoma which is what
seven point so again he's flipping to
his other source
and that one says I nurtured dick back
can't wait
there's the word gear
yeah transformation
and Kenyan means uh problems in your
life okay Kenyan means problems in your
life it means bad factors okay and then
he says change it to the lum
okay change your
change your everyday challenges
into a path to Buddhism okay which is
wild success okay all right
um
then there's a picture I want to show
you
I have a lot of fun finding these
pictures as you may have guessed and
this one's perfect okay and you'll see
why
all right so here's uh
he's like a young scientist and he has a
great idea okay
I am gonna test you on the idioms okay
either means idea image it doesn't mean
88 image okay so don't worry all right
now
by the way you have to read this as NASA
I just made a note to myself because Che
patana is a very common word
and you could misread this sentence but
Tibetan doesn't Japan has spaces
between every
syllable
so how is Joel doing today it would be
her
is Sir Joe will do and maybe it will do
is a word you see I mean
uh
so he says
NASA
sickness
ja
means enemies
uh you can say competitors in your life
for your position at work or for your
wife or whatever J means uh demons okay
foreign
[Music]
means things you don't want okay things
that are not happy
and here's a very very deep idea coming
up this morning and uh if you don't go
home with anything else tomorrow
go home with this idea okay here's one
idea you can take home
and it will help you for the rest of
your life okay
uh and it's and it's subtle it takes a
few minutes to get it okay
Human Nature
is to blame something else for your
problems human Leyland means blame
Shen La gel means loaded on somebody
else blame it on anything else except
me
the human nature
is to
mentally
at all costs avoid the idea that all
this crap is your fault okay human
nature and and it's very difficult to
overcome that nature it's very difficult
to fight that nature
human being
nature is to want to blame somebody else
for your problems and it's deeper than
you think okay he's not saying the
person sitting next to you in the temple
at Diamond Mountain it's deeper than
that okay you ready
people have real trouble
to acknowledge
that all the problems that come to them
are Karma
okay they they desperately want to blame
something else
and and it's not necessarily other
people
okay and he says
people will say
I got sick because I ate the wrong thing
my my illness is because of my diet
okay or done into bed
I bumped into a spirit being at the
bathroom
which seems to be where they come from
okay right sometimes they break the
bathroom uh
so it was Human Nature uh in Tibet
that when you had a medical problem
people would say I must I must be eating
the wrong stuff you know maybe I'm
missing some kind of vitamin or nutrient
you know maybe I should change my diet
or in Tibet they would say I must have
bumped into a spirit being when I was
going past the bathroom you know they'll
say I don't know what happened but I was
fine when I left the temple
and then I went over there and then when
I got back I didn't feel so well
and I must have picked up a spirit being
it's called done
I must have picked up a spirit being on
the way okay what do we call it now
viruses and germs and it's not different
it's the same okay I must have got a
virus I must have got a germ he says
that's as primitive as saying I picked
up a demon in the bathroom
okay you are not different
from people in Tibet who never heard of
a germ or a virus you're doing the same
thing they did okay oh and I I must have
picked up a germ from somebody you know
I must have been uh at the Jetson
compass center and I shouldn't have sat
at that table with that person coughing
and he says wake up man
it's not the virus that made you sick
and he's pissed off he feels pissed off
he's like listen
don't be superstitious don't say I
picked up a demon at the Jetson Carpet
Center somewhere near where Rob was
sitting
you know you're just doing the same
mindset that these
superstitious Tibetans who never heard
of science
is an is an advanced superstition
okay
picture the old one
got it
okay duh duh okay it's not the viruses
okay
okay it's not the Kobe virus all right
wake up
it's not you know demon number 36. uh
behind the Rock at Dime Mountain you
know give it up
what stop blaming it on other things
okay
it could be a virus
it could be a demon
who made the fires
[Music]
where'd it come from
okay that's like blaming the air
why'd you get covered oxygen
huh
so what are you gonna do stop breathing
Maybe
why why are you oxygen oxygen carries
the virus if I didn't have oxygen I
could be better
you know like you're blaming the
you're blaming the
what do you call it you're blaming the
instrument and not the real Source
you're blaming what brought it to you
the wind
oh the wind gave me coven no the wind
didn't give you coven the the viruses
that floated on the Wind from the other
person's mouth gave you Kobe no that
Karma that floated the viruses to the
wind of the other person's mouth is what
gave you covered stop blaming it on
stupid things
who created the wind coming from the
other person's mouth
okay when you have a medical problem
uh focus on the real cause
and and
take care of it and and take care of it
and then you don't have to
it's probably cheaper right
okay
take care of the karma
does that mean you shouldn't go to a
doctor
my llama used to say take care of the
karma and then go to the doctor
okay
and that's that's a good strategy okay
did gesla say don't go to a doctor I
didn't say that I go to a doctor
but take care of the karma before you go
to the doctor
okay and then the doctor will work
and it saves money also I'm sorry my
computer's dying here I go okay come on
back honey
uh by the time you get up here it always
starts working
uh
and if you don't come up here it doesn't
start working
okay wait wait I got it
so it's kind of
you gotta think like that okay is it
your diet it could be your diet
but I got this this irritating guys if
you ever lived in New York City right
Rob
you're on the subway and there's this
buff
thin
handsome guys eating chocolate bars on
the on the subway and you're like dang
you know uh how they do that
must be
Karma come on you guys
I got this
oh here we go okay
they call it the wheel of death
it's almost like I'm supposed to
contemplate before I go on
um
okay here we go
yeah people blame things on on germs
which in the old days was called
sickness demons right
said I'm doing so
camper I put viruses and carcinogens
okay that's my translation of done
done means sickness demon
okay and the way what the doctors in
Tibet did was come over and hit you on
the head with a brick or something and
that was supposed to stop the sickness
demons okay nowadays they just radiate
you or something or give you
chemotherapy
it's the same primitive thing okay it's
not different from
blood lending or hitting somebody with a
stick because they have a demon in them
it's the same thing chemo and hitting
people with a stick to get the demons
out of them it's the same thing it's
exactly the same thing if you don't take
care of the
Karma it's not going to do anything okay
okay so what should you do not do chemo
I didn't say that take care of the karma
then do chemo or do chemo and take do
the karma really fast
take care of this camera really fast so
um
next paragraph
is very important here Kanda took means
Sawa means root right
means root
Carla took this is a very important
practice next image Daniel
who is that that's Colombo okay you guys
don't know Colombo if you're not from
America uh so in 1973
when my llama discovered the demon
called
television
uh some guy really some guy I think the
guy was a demon I really believe it
bought him a television
and that was the end and uh he's like
bang on the floor at eight o'clock at
night he lived upstairs I built his
house
uh and I he had a two-story house and he
would bang on the floor and I was
supposed to run up the stairs and watch
Colombo with him and Colombo's like
Sherlock Holmes detective and he he
always has a cigar
Peter Falk and his goes uh I saw you
didn't kill your husband right and the
lady said no why would I do that and
he'd say well why is that hair brush
under the chair
like
oh it just fell down he said yeah yeah
it wasn't it didn't fall down while you
were stabbing him
and she'd go ah you got me you know
he was so funny he was always like hmm
you know
why is this up here
be a detective for God's sake be a Karma
detective you know hey I got a medical
problem yeah what's a problem
what's the comma what comma did I do and
uh be a detector you know be a Karma
detector cure yourself heal yourself
okay go to a doctor yes during the
treatment yes but uh like look at what's
the real problem trace it back
and he's always doing that he's like why
why is the hairbrush out of the chair
you know
and
he never says it directly he always gets
the person to confess he just irritates
them until they say okay okay I killed
my husband
now leave me alone
so your Karma's gonna say yeah you don't
care it's me
it wasn't the virus it wasn't to come in
it wasn't the
the plastic in your water bottle
that gave you cancer you know it was
it was your karma okay what you did does
that mean you should use plastic water
bottles no it's bad for the environment
and it puts plastic
molecules all over your guts and you get
cancer so yeah
but stop the karma also or else your
aluminum bottle will do something to you
okay all right
[Music]
mendipa means stuff you never wanted
okay.com is what sugam.com
desire realm
means all the stuff you never desired
it's the same verb okay uh stuff you
never wanted
uh happens
say means the total amount the word say
here which means measure like SEMA right
so again pramana
same means the total amount okay
everything you never wanted to happen
Lincoln Champa
Lake
it was created by
Karma don't blame you know carcinogens
don't blame viruses
well guessler so should we just cough in
someone's face if we have covid I didn't
say that
I suggest you ask them to wear a mask
and take care of your karma but maybe
not in that order
okay all right thinking
now now he says something very deep I
will give how much can I give wife 300
bucks for an extraordinary answer
okay
tracing back like
Colombo
who put the hairbrush under the chair
there
and then and then go back one step
before the hairbrush
okay we traced it back to Karma we got
it all back to comma
where'd the comma come from
what's he say here
what they say here
yeah self cherishing taking care of
yourself first okay you want to cure a
medical problem go after the karma you
want to cure the karma
go after the
self taking care of yourself first go
after taking care of yourself first it's
an easy way to take care of the karma
okay all right just take care of the
karma what do you mean what am I
supposed to do like try to remove all
the bad stuff I ever did not you don't
have to go go to the root of the karma
what's the root of the karma
taking care of yourself first did I say
you shouldn't take care of yourself
I never said that and I don't want any
martyrs the Dharma Martyrs are the most
irritating people
oh you take all the pastries I can do
without you know he said but there's
enough for both of us
yeah but you take them
you know I mean it's really irritating
because we know you stuck your face with
pastries right after we leave
okay
so
be a Colombo okay you might want to buy
a cigar for this
me and Veronica took her sister Monica
to Paris and we know he got off the
plane we checked in the hotel we went
out for our first walk next to the
Louvre we found a square there was a
beautiful Cafe
and we sat down and had a nice French
coffee which is like the whole goal is
spending all that money by the way we
were there on business
uh right remember
we married somebody in there
and uh
and there was a cigar shop next to the
coffee and we said we all looked at each
other at the same moment we said let's
smoke a cigar and we never smoked a
cigar before and and we all we went and
bought one cigar and we walked around
Paris and smoked a cigar together
so you might want to do that
so you look like Colombo
and then and you're saying okay
this this problem in my life it must be
Karma
and then be a detective be a detective
what's the next step
what triggered the karma
taking care of myself first it's so
simple okay I don't I can't understand
the karma yeah you cannot it takes a
Buddha
but I'll give you a guideline what's a
guideline
um
you took care of yourself first at some
point somewhere somehow you took care of
yourself first you want to fix it yeah
okay genius
we'll give you a genius Grant
[Music]
stop
until you get yourself first I didn't
say
don't take care of yourself I said equal
rights equal rights
other people have equal rights to your
time do they have exclusive rights to
your time no should you hurt yourself to
serve others
okay should you not sleep should you
drive all night
and dangerously endanger yourself
right
I'm talking a lady behind you okay
you should take care of yourself
or you can't take care of others because
you'll you'll get in a car accident or
something okay good all right all right
so I need to took means took is very
important here
took means uh to meet somebody or to
make contact okay
okay here wrong two
that's the end of the detective work it
goes back that far and it stops that's
the
the buck stops there the the
Chase back your your problem
I got carcinogens I have a bad diet I
got viruses I got Spirit beings that
were hanging out in the bathroom
and and then I traced it back to my
karma and then I traced that back to
take care of myself first tooth means
that's the end of the road there's no
there's no place behind that
because you've been doing that for
billions of years
there's nothing before that except more
of that okay there's
what's the cause of taking his hair care
yourself first
taking care of yourself first for
billions of years for countless years
okay if you get your mental process
your detective work
if you go back as far as
taking care of yourself first you can
relax you hit the root cause you found
the cause of cancer
okay you don't have to be a scientist to
find the cause of cancer just go back
that far talk means that's it you hit
the real cars and you don't have to go
back further than that okay all right
Columbo uh
and I put the English there for you it's
a very unusual word okay
if you're looking to figure out why
somebody broke into your car
and took your purse or something he says
try to work back past the thief
you know don't go running around the
neighborhood looking for somebody with
your purse
okay try to trace it
if your purse is missing don't go
looking for people with your purse go
looking for the karma and then go look
for the
taking care of yourself that caused the
karma and you can relax
your personal comeback
okay
okay and what he says here is it's not
enough to walk around the neighborhood
and try to find someone who's carrying
your purse Kuma means deceive okay
[Music]
your Le
men means bad bad karma it's your bad
karma what's he gonna say in the next
sentence anticipatory translation we try
to teach it to the mixed nuts close your
eyes and guess what the next sentence
says
yeah and that goes back to taking care
of yourself let's confirm thank you
trace it back to your taking care of
yourself first
a great translation skill
is to anticipate what the guy has to be
saying next you can close your eyes at
the last sentence
and and translate the next sentence
without seeing it
and then you can check you know and and
and it's a great translation hell okay
it's a it's a great skill for a
translator guess what he has to say next
write the sentence down and then fix it
it's very fun
when you think like
a llama you will be able to write the
next sentence on your own
and you'll be right
cool
all right uh Danny says uh I got a new
picture for you it's 28a
sent you a new picture this morning just
after my coffee
uh anyway it's a traditional Tibetan
people there
well we'll figure it out
you can put it up when you find it okay
it's a piece of wood
um
[Music]
so when you get
when you fall when you get sick
when something happens to your body
mean means we get a problem of some kind
of told that joke to
now he switches gears he says therefore
to be sick is a lucky thing
because it will force you to think about
Karma which will force you to think
about
you must have taken care of yourself
first okay okay all right he says it's
drunk what's joke about you guys
friend you know friend dopo is a nice
Tibetan word what's the Sanskrit
Mitra Mitra okay like Derma Mitchell
means Dharma friend
someone
and my tree comes from that maitrea
comes from that
ultimate friend okay nice dogs have some
good day in
uh getting sick
is the prostration board for
for your Bad Karma so did you find the
preservation born yet
it didn't come in
oh
it just was coming from The Retreat
Valley it wasn't that far
anyway I
there's a special wooden board
that's about this one
and you put special gloves on your hands
and you do full body prostrations on it
okay and it's angled slightly up at the
end
so you go down and you slide and then
you come back and you stand up I went
down to Benton doctor recently
and she's like you gotta get attraction
I'm like come on
and because my llama did they did like
500 prosperations I don't have time for
this
I'd rather go to the gym but it's the
same thing okay it's it's tibetan's like
llamas like chalk Shing to prostration
board
because they can collect some good karma
while they're doing the gym
it's an interesting idea but it's really
bad for your niece
and uh
so anyway
uh he says
uh
thinking about
thinking about where your sicknesses is
really coming from
is your prostration board
work out your sicknesses
on your prostration Board of
intelligence Dharma intelligence this
the board the prostration board is your
Dharma intelligence
he says when you feel when you feel
physically not well do a daily workout
on your prostration board which is
meditations on Karma
and meditations on
taking care of yourself first okay
that's your prostration board then go to
the gym then do your workout okay but
but don't expect a workout to help you
if you don't have the right intention
okay you have to make new make new
resolutions about taking care of others
first then go to the gym
and work out your high blood pressure or
something okay
is it wrong to go to the gym to work out
your high blood pressure no it's smart
but do it with style
okay like think about
while you're working out think of the
times that you were taking care of
yourself first and then the workout will
work got it
all right uh
you didn't find it didn't show up bro
that's okay nah that's a different guy
well this is a good let's do him
uh
he has succeeded at something all right
so get that feeling in your heart okay I
don't know he got a promotion or he won
an election or he lost an election and
thinks he won the election
I don't know
okay uh
no politics championship
then he says uh
Championship
now he's going to a new topic okay now
he's going to a new topic
when you do get sick knots are
whatever you get
if you think about it when you get sick
you should
celebrate like that guy why
you just used up some Bad Karma
yay
did you get covered yet no oh you know
don't worry you're a good person you'll
get it you know okay you can wear off
your wear off your Bad Karma
that's a teacher yeah
[Music]
Denny says if you think about it
if by the way we're gonna do a q a in 10
minutes okay so get ready if you're
online
send your questions to Timothy all right
it's a very difficult word and uh all my
vocabulary came from
direct contact with my llama we lived
together for 25 years
we would say things at me about me and I
had to figure them out and he's on
coaching and uh you know
I didn't have a dictionary I had him
uh and I I can remember where he taught
me all my work most of my words I can
remember where I learned it you know and
uh I don't know remember
we were building a sidewalk together
around the temple in how we built the
addition and then we had this
increase the sidewalk so people could
walk around the temple and the house
and we did the sidewalk together you
know and uh
he's I'm like we did the truck comms we
pour the concrete and he looks at me and
he says you got the trial and I'm like
you got the child the trial is the thing
you make the cement level when I'm like
he's got you got the trial I said no you
got the trial he says I don't got the
trial and I'm like what are we gonna do
and he he grabs a piece of wooden he
says go check
okay and I'm like let's go chill and he
says we can use this as a trowel
okay so let's go to
yeah substitute that's a good who said
that that's pretty good
yeah acceptable substitute not the real
thing
but it's an acceptable substitute okay
so he says here
if you do get coven that's a gocha for
cleaning up your karma
okay are you intelligent enough to clean
up your karma in advance no
so what's the next best thing get
covered
okay then you should be happy
wow I didn't have a trial trial means
you confess your karma with the four
powers and you cleaned it up but you
weren't smart enough to do that so what
happened you got coveted yay I got
coming
it's it's a substitute for uh
for
it's a substitute for doing confession
it's a little bit late
okay you get sick if you had done your
four powers you wouldn't have got sick
but since you didn't do your four powers
you got sick you should celebrate you
should be happy
wow that's as good as doing the four
powers what the Bad Karma comes back to
me at a lower level
you trigger a premature baby
okay and that's a Dharma skill that you
have to learn okay it's triggering a
premature baby okay try to get the karma
to ripen before it's cancer
before you get cancer
try to get the karma to ripen
prematurely
okay
before you get cancer the the karma that
was gonna give you cancer
try to trigger it early okay how do you
trigger an early
you make a decision to take on other
people's problems
and that triggers the karma early that
triggers a premature baby it's a very
cool practice okay
so
you decide voluntarily I will take on
Shin tian's Karma tell me anything you
did in the last few weeks I'll take it I
I voluntarily accept your karma can you
take another person's Karma you cannot
can you get a lot of good karma by
deciding to try to take someone else's
Karma yes
that good karma is so strong that it
will trigger a premature baby
okay and that will go chipper it's as
good as the four powers
it's a little late and it's a little
messy
but it better late than never
okay so uh
if you if you're not smart enough
to do the four powers in advance
at least try to take on other people's
Karma okay
okay and that will trigger an early
ripening of your own Karma got it okay
tension
to do something you cannot do
is enough to trigger your karma early
okay cause income and that's all wrapped
up in The Wheel of Life teaching
uh limbs number eight and nine links
number eight and nine
and I think so gang's book finished
yesterday or something he's cleaning now
he's doing the final cleaning which
takes a long time so you'll get it
before you're 90. I promise
okay maybe not before I'm 90. okay
[Music]
means giddy giddy happiness
means
do you feel hun no okay just trying to
do something for somebody else to take
their Bad Karma
and then yeah
okay got it
if you're not walking around like this
by the second class
means I did it I did it what I got
coming yes you know okay
no really uh if you're if you're really
doing a retreat
and you're trying to take other people's
the sign that your tongue line is
successful is that you will have a small
karmic disaster
like you'll get covered
when you're taking out that boy finally
that you've been tasting for weeks and
and then you get covered the night
before okay and then you should be I did
it
okay all right
uh and that's that guy's picture we got
five minutes to q a all right
stop
that means well
don't do
tender okay
oh I I God think yeah what happened I
got I did it I I was trying to take
someone else's Carmine and I got sick it
worked you know done through what
a moga City
there's two translations in Sanskrit of
dandrum one is a moga City
tantric Theory
gets everything done what's the
non-tendering word
Siddhartha
Siddhartha is the name of the prince who
became Buddha okay his name means
uh did it
okay
means did it Arta means go
siddharata means I did it
[Music]
okay that should be a good name for
someone taking bodies off of us
I did it Siddhartha
Siddhartha
okay he's the daughter
it's got a ring to it Tim
we gotta's name somebody is
you got names for everybody right I
don't have to wait you got names for
everybody right I don't have to worry
about it right
yeah okay
so if there's someone
who who signs up late
like in 10 minutes
for the bodhisattva ceremony I give you
permission to call them Hong Kong Ginger
okay which means
okay all right
means you should be super happy
again God came into you should be super
happy so if you try to take other
people's Karma
and then you have just a normal life
disaster you can blame it on your
practice
and go he I did it okay all right okay
and then you can say I pray the rest of
the crap comes to me also okay I like I
got two percent of my karma just ripened
I got I got covered now I pray that 98
comes I hope I get cancer on top of it
you know okay by the way that's a weird
prayer to make but if you could make it
you'd be a happy person
with cancer
okay because you used up hell Karma or
something all right a real Buddhist
would be happy
to have a serious medical problem
just after they tried to do all these
practices they would be Long Hong
okay and that's a hard
to believe but it's true okay if if you
get good
at Tongan and you have a major problem
you should be really happy
because because the karma you just used
up was hell realm Karma okay
and and it's a lot better to get a
serious illness than go to the house
okay you should be ecstatic
that something bad happened to you
Margie to your legs
all right good good job okay all right
means pray that you get the rest to
ripen also okay
I pray that my illness should code
chippa for the karma of all living
beings
substitute substitute for okay I pray
that my current medical problems
get some mileage out of your medical
problems I went in for gallbladder
surgery it was the funniest one of the
funniest moments of my life I was in
intense pain for 24 hours in my retreat
cabin
I came down here to teach
I was laying on the floor
and I had to go to the hospital
and Jing Mason waiting to drag me to her
car and
guess she's low tires like oh I wrote a
long line pair can you just hang on a
while and I'm like I'm like guess what I
can't get off the floor and he says
that's okay you stay there and let me
read the long line pair and I said I'm
going to be the only llama who ever died
during his long life time
and he's like but he wrote it he wrote
it for like six months and I I could see
he really wanted to doing so we did it
anyway uh gold chipper okay when you get
a problem
think that oh this should
substitute
for everyone else's Karma okay got it Go
chip nice word right go chirping
I'm gonna stop there
and we'll go to q a for about 15 minutes
and then we'll take a break okay
um
a substitute for another guy I look
pretty tall but my heels are high
that's an old hippie song
sorry what that was loud
so the question
um let's see where does it go
is could you because of these beautiful
tongue lens service grants someone's
asking a question about
could you give us some advice on how to
manage our resources in a beautiful and
meaningful way especially if we're
receiving money from a Dharma job
how to balance things in our lives with
receiving such
precious money and not wasting it yeah
good question that's a great question so
uh
I don't know for the first 15 years of
ACI and diamond mountain
we nobody got paid nobody got anything I
did the whole 15 years of
of ACI courses I paid for everything and
I was seriously in debt by the time that
were processed was finished I was in
Houston and uh
and I I didn't get paid nobody got paid
and I had to pay for all the
notebooks and everything and the travel
and and then um
people started to help
and then people started to overhelm
and uh you know we started to give
some uh hourly payment to some of the
people and by the way we're not past
that
we don't have enough money to pay
everybody
what you can make
outside and that's just the way it is
you know but but we can
the dongland service grants
are meant to help you with your expenses
and I'm thinking of people like the
translators
there's there's online translators now
because we went online
there's people who are spending six or
eight hours a day translating
and they don't get anything they don't
make anything and we're trying to uh get
make we're trying to create these grants
uh to and to try to help people with
their expenses okay and by the way to do
to make a commitment to your marriage
or your partner and then make the
commitment of having children for
example
and making a commitment to a mortgage
and a car
monthly payment
uh and then go Dharma
and uh and give up all your commitments
that you already made is not done
okay that's just bad karma okay it's and
I'll repeat
uh you make commitments in your life uh
to your family to your car payments to
your mortgage
parents you know taking care of your
parents you make commitments
and then you become a Dharma person you
sign up for Dharma translator
and it's tempting to say
well I'll just give up my own
commitments because now I'm I'm on a new
I'm on an enlightened track
and that's an enlightened track to the
hell Realms something like that okay so
you made promises you gotta keep them
okay uh so the Dharma grants the Tongan
service grants
they are meant to help people keep their
commitments
uh to to taking care of other people
your family your your wife or husband
your your parents you know you need to
do that so uh we're trying to make sure
people get some payment it's not we
don't have enough money to pay you
you know you're probably worth a hundred
thousand we can only probably pay you
twenty thousand or something because we
don't have them it's not enough money uh
but I think it's a great
opportunity as I said
um
to take a year off or take two years off
and
support yourself and do some cool Dharma
work and then go back to your corporate
job or something like that I'm I'm
thinking that would be a cool I wish I
had had this opportunity
um my grandmother died and my mother
died in the same few months and my
grandma was wealthy and my mother had
nothing but the money went boom boom and
uh so I could do my geshi degree without
working you know I didn't have to work I
had this money so uh we're trying to
give you
support to be able to do Dharma work now
that money
is a severe responsibility yeah that's
true
so it took me uh
it took me 25 years 30 years
to raise money to pay people and and
then I started paying people
and and I saw two things happen
number one
some people worked really hard
and and very successful extremely
successful like Tim
and and they just did really really good
work in
and then some people
took the money and stopped working you
know and I I don't know what to do about
these people I I'm I'm in a bad
situation I'm in a what do you call it
yeah I don't I don't know what to do to
be honest I got money for somebody
they're taking a salary and they stop
working and I'm like
you know and uh that's yeah that's a
very serious Karma to to waste
uh Dharma resources is a very serious
Karma so think about it
if you take Dharma money
you gotta put in the word you got to
give the word you got to do the work so
so don't take a grant from the dungland
service grants and stop working okay
that's extremely serious Karma yeah so
that's all I can say and you know I mean
I you don't have to be a genius
to know that right and you know if
you're working hard and you know if
you're not working hard and and that's
up to you but to take the money
and not to work hard is is a karmic
disaster okay so uh I don't have to tell
you that you can figure that out but
it's yeah it's much more heavy
Karma money
so if you take if you take this
organization's money if you take a grant
uh to do some work for goodness sake do
it okay or or are you or it's very bad
karma and I have these people they get a
grant
they don't work
they keep losing money and they're like
they come to me and they say I don't
know what's happening
things are happening I'm getting all
these big expenses and I don't know why
and I'm like maybe you're not working
maybe you're not using the money we're
giving you uh maybe you're not doing the
work you're getting paid for and they're
like oh
you don't have to beat Columbo to figure
that out all right but but it's a ticket
to uh long-term Financial stress
you see what I mean if you take Dharma
money and you don't produce
you will be stressed out financially for
many years
and and that's that's painful that's
really painful so
so okay so you're just protecting
yourself either either quit and say look
I'll do as much as I can without money
uh or or or or give it your best and it
doesn't mean you have to overwork
when you overwork you do lousy work
and nobody wants your lousy work okay
when you take care of yourself
and you do your practice you do your
meditations
you study you do your Retreats and you
do your Dharma work that's sweet okay
but to overwork
and don't sleep get make yourself sick
that's not what we're asking we're
asking you to do a fair amount of work
for a fair amount of less than a fair
amount of pay okay and uh so yeah be
careful with Dharma money it's very
dangerous but
get a grant
and you and you do what you're supposed
to do it's extremely good karma
and you will be financially successful
strangely
financially successful you know I gave
away 3 000 bucks this morning before I
got here
just you know like that and uh if you
if you followed the karma
rules
the the money just come like crazy well
forty thousand dollars since
since yesterday morning okay
that's not bad
uh okay all right Timothy back to you
so we have one question here I'm going
to summarize it um during their
meditation
as soon as they focus on the object
their body begins to shake or they begin
to to laugh
or they're beginning to get very tense
in their body tense tense yes okay so
the question is what can they do to
navigate this or what should they be
doing differently so that they're not
because it's uncomfortable and it
doesn't seem like it's meditation yeah
okay understand
um
so when you're meditating
uh because of long Sam dupa two
what's that you give me the buoy Arizona
version
yeah the cowboy on the horn okay
uh the piranha the thoughts are writing
on The Prana right
the Cowboys on the horse Okay so uh
while you're meditating
uh your thought processes are affecting
your subtle body heavily
so uh as as you sit with your eyes
closed
silently without moving on your
meditation cushion
and you are messing with the cowboy the
horse will
you know if you do a big change with the
cowboy
the horse will move okay and it's very
common to see a person who's meditating
to to go like this
you know uh or or your body like a jolt
or something like that or you start
shaking like that
so you gotta get familiar with your
subtle body
and you gotta know what's a good jolt
and what's a bad jolt okay so I'm gonna
give you some jolt guidelines
[Music]
a sudden jump like that is probably good
okay that's a sudden release of Prana if
you're doing yoga
and you start burping
uh oddly you know like uh every every
every post
that's a good sign okay that's uh
promise being released uh stagnant
Prana is being released and you will
burp or you'll fart or you'll sweat and
and in the yoga tradition that's
considered highly successful sweaty
burping farting yogis
are successful yogis okay it's not fun
to be around them
but uh you are Prana is being released
and by the way it will stop after a
while and by the way you will get small
injuries uh as Prana moves when you
start yoga so the first year that you do
yoga
you will get small injuries you will
hurt your neck or you'll get a bad
shoulder and just work through it
because it's Prana is being released
that was jammed up it was stagnant it
was stuck so don't be concerned if you
if your first year or two years that you
do yoga
or the first year or two years that you
meditate did I say regularly
uh you will have this sudden releases of
Prana and that's a good thing okay if
you do hurt something in yoga like your
knee or your shoulder I had a shoulder
thing
in three year Retreat I had a shoulder
thing for the first six months or
something
then take care of it don't
don't like trying to do more Prana
moving
care of it don't don't hurt it more
but understand that that it might be a
good thing you're releasing promise so
if you have jolts going on in your
meditation
generally that's a good sign okay and
but if you have shaking okay
okay start shaking
that's not a good sign okay that means
you have a
overload of Prana and not a release of
Prana okay so what how do you get an
overload of Prana you meditate too much
you meditate more than your capacity
or you're focusing at your heart chakra
so somehow your focus
is in here
okay and then that tends to cause uh
shaking and quaking of your hands and
stuff like that okay and that's because
you are for you know you may not be
doing it consciously you may not be
trying to visualize
your teacher at your heart but if you're
generally focused at your heart and
you're meditating
when you start getting shakes that's a
overload of Prana and it's a bad thing
and it will get worse
and there's a simple uh traditional
correction which is to drop that
visualization to your navel okay uh so
drop anytime you get shaky which is a
bad sign
and purposely drop the visualization
to your navel it's not at your navel
it's behind your navel so that's really
important okay you're not meditating on
your belly button go to your belly
button and go back
towards your spine so like an inch or
two in front of your spine okay so go to
the belly button turn left go in okay
and take the visualization back towards
the spine but not in the spine okay not
in the spinal column
they say half an inch in front of the
spinal column park there do the
visualization there the shaking will
stop okay and and if you're shaking you
have to you have to take care of it or
it will get worse okay and and then it
will cost
irritation uh
with your loved ones then your
meditation is like a
Glacier meditation
like you're
you'll become more irritated and
irritating at the same time okay so
that's a general guideline uh
by the way that's why it's important to
uh have a teacher okay like it's it's
it's really important to have a
relationship with a person who's done
long retreats
and can tell you the difference between
a jolt and a shame okay and uh you need
someone who can teach you these things
the nice thing about diamond mountain
Retreat Center
is of all the retreat centers in the
whole world we probably have more
three-year retreatens related to this
Retreat Center than any other Retreat
Center including Tibet
so uh I think we're lucky to have the
staff here at Diamond Mountain we have
experienced
meditators here
who survived a three-year entry and uh
and they're they know their stuff
because they they've been there and they
made mistakes and they they learned
so so probably the best thing about
jolts
or Shanks is to find a good meditation
teacher who can help you
and it doesn't have to be it's if it's
in person it's better but if it's online
I mean that's better than nothing right
so we have people like that at Diamond
Mountain get in touch with diamond
mountain
we can assign someone to you right okay